Princeton University Library Collection on Slavery in the Americas, 1700-1888 (bulk 1790-1863): Finding Aid C1210
Manuscripts Division
Princeton University Library Collection on Slavery in the Americas
1700-1888
1790-1863
Manuscripts Division
Princeton University Library. Special Collections.
C1210
4 boxes
6.1 linear feet
Consists of a closed collection of documents related to slavery, the trade of enslaved persons, and the colonial plantation economy, particularly in the United States, the Caribbean, and Brazil in the 18th and 19th centuries.
Scope and Contents
Consists of a closed collection of documents related to slavery, the trade of enslaved persons, and the colonial plantation economy, particularly in the United States, the Caribbean, and Brazil in the 18th and 19th centuries. This miscellaneous collection provides a way of locating small accessions of slavery-related material acquired by the Library from various sources.
The majority of the collection consists of bills of sale, plantation inventories, and other records created by European colonists documenting the sale and valuation of enslaved men, women, and children in the United States, including New Jersey, New York, Tennessee, Louisiana, Kentucky, South Carolina, Georgia, and Mississippi; the Three Mile River Estate in Westmoreland, Jamaica; the Mount Charles (Middleton) Plantation in Saint Thomas Parish, Jamaica, which was owned by Sir Henry Clinton (1738?-1795); and the plantation estate of John Lavicount in Antigua. Also present is a document containing statistics on enslaved populations for each state copied from the United States Census of 1790, as well as a 1820 deed of freedom for a formerly enslaved man in Brazil.
There are also several indentures for domestic apprenticeship or enslavement of African American and multiracial children in Delaware, Massachusetts, New Jersey, and New York, which date from the 1790s through the 1820s, including for two children apprenticed to United States Representative Killian K. Van Rensselaer (1763-1845) of New York.
Materials related to ships involved in the transatlantic trade in enslaved Africans include a price list taken from the log of the English merchant ship Daniel and Henry, which was employed along the Gold Coast of West Africa (1700); an account book for the French privateer ship Républicaine (1798-1799); and a sales agreement and invoice for the cargo of the American ship Favourite (1804).
Additional letters and documents pertain to efforts to extend slavery throughout the Americas, including copied documents regarding the status of enslaved and free people of color following the British capture of Martinique from French colonial rule in 1794; a letter between French generals working to suppress revolutionary efforts during the Haitian Revolution; and a letter between United States politicians regarding congressional debates over the expansion of slavery into the California and New Mexico territories in the late 1840s.
The Documents on Slavery in Brazil file group consists of 77 miscellaneous legal and other documents, as well as one book, dating from 1758 to 1888, pertaining to the history of the history of slavery in Brazil as a Portuguese colony and later as the Empire of Brazil, until the abolition of slavery in 1887. Titles and description are transcribed exactly as they are on the dealer's inventory received with the materials. The folder numbers correspond with the item number in the dealer's inventory.
This collection was formerly referred to as the "Miscellaneous Slavery Collection." No additions will be made to this collection. Accessions relating to this topic will be added to the General Manuscripts Miscellaneous Collection (C0140).
Arrangement
Materials are grouped by accession.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was formed in 2007 as a result of a departmental practice of combining into one collection material of various accessions relating to a particular person, family, or subject. Materials have been acquired through multiple purchases and gifts.
Appraisal
No material was removed from the collection during 2017-2019 processing.
Separated Materials
During 2017 processing, materials that did not fit into the topical scope of slavery in the Americas were separated and placed into different collections. Simeon Johnson materials (AM 16859) were separated and made into a collection: Simeon Johnson Papers (C1589). Two Frederick Douglass letters (AM 12182), a William Ellery manuscript (AM 2013-59), and military correspondence regarding African American soldiers in Tennessee after the Civil War (AM 12182) were separated and placed into the General Manuscripts Miscellaneous Collection (C0140).
African Americans -- Social conditions -- 19th century -- Sources.; Indentured servants -- Delaware -- History -- 19th century -- Sources.; Indentured servants -- Massachusetts -- History -- 18th century -- Sources.; Indentured servants -- New York (State) -- History -- 19th century -- Sources.; Plantation owners -- Caribbean Area -- History -- 18th century -- Sources.; Plantation owners -- Caribbean Area -- History -- 19th century -- Sources.; Plantation owners -- United States -- History -- 19th century -- Sources.; Prices -- Guinea -- 18th century -- Sources.; Privateering -- France -- History -- 18th century -- Sources.; Slave bills of sale -- Georgia -- 19th century.; Slave bills of sale -- Kentucky -- 19th century.; Slave bills of sale -- Louisiana -- 19th century.; Slave bills of sale -- New Jersey -- 19th century.; Slave bills of sale -- New York (State) -- 19th century.; Slave bills of sale -- South Carolina -- 19th century.; Slave bills of sale -- Tennessee -- 19th century.; Slave records -- Brazil -- 18th century.; Slave records -- Jamaica -- 18th century.; Slave records -- Jamaica -- 19th century.; Slave records -- Kentucky -- 19th century.; Slave trade -- Africa, West -- History -- 18th century -- Sources.; Slave trade -- United States -- History -- 19th century -- Sources.; Slaveholders -- Caribbean Area -- History -- 19th century -- Sources.; Slaveholders -- United States -- History -- 19th century -- Sources.; Slave traders -- Rhode Island -- History -- 19th century -- Sources.; Slavery -- Antigua -- History -- 19th century -- Sources.; Slavery -- Brazil -- History -- 19th century -- Sources.; Slavery -- Jamaica -- History -- 19th century -- Sources.; Slavery -- United States -- History -- 19th century -- Sources.; Slaves -- Emancipation -- Brazil -- History -- 19th century -- Sources.; Slaves -- United States -- Census, 1790.; Brazil -- History -- 18th century -- Sources.; England -- Commerce -- Guinea -- 18th century.; Guinea -- Commerce -- England -- 18th century.; Haiti -- History -- Revolution, 1791-1804 -- Sources.; Jamaica -- History -- 18th century -- Sources.; Martinique -- History -- 18th century -- Sources.; United States -- History -- 1783-1865 -- Sources.; Account books -- 18th century.; Bills of sale -- 19th century.; Deeds -- 19th century.; Estate records -- 19th century.; Financial records -- 19th century.; Free papers -- 19th century.; Indentures -- 19th century.; Legal documents -- 19th century.; Price lists -- 18th century.; Africa; American history; Black history; European history; Van Rensselaer, K. K. (Killian Killian), 1763-1845; Clinton, Henry, Sir
- Price List of Goods Carried by the Daniel and Henry to the Guinea Coast for Trade, 1700 October 10; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  Scope and Contents
  Consists of a price list taken from the log of the merchant ship Daniel and Henry that sailed for the Guinea Coast of Africa from Dartmouth, England, on February 24, 1700, with a cargo of goods valued at £2252 in the care of Walter Prideaux. Prideaux has marked 37 of the 48 items listed as particularly recommended for Gold Coast trading.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  AM 2009-50
  Purchased in November 2008.
- Indenture for the Sale of Mount Charles Plantation, Jamaica, to Sir Henry Clinton (1738?-1795), 1774; 1 box (Box Z-000005)
  Consists of a manuscript indenture in six parts on four vellum sheets (70 x 90cm) recording the sale, for £12,000, of the Mount Charles Plantation in Saint Thomas Parish, Jamaica, to Sir Henry Clinton (1738?-1795), a British army officer and politician who sat in the House of Commons between 1772 and 1795 and served as Commander-in-Chief of the British forces during the American Revolutionary War. The sale included the Mount Charles Plantation (later known as the Middleton Plantation), as well as another parcel of land known as "Middleton Penn," 247 enslaved laborers (all of whom are listed by name and occupation), and all future children born to the enslaved women listed.
  The indenture first recites a deed dated September 24, 1768, which was the original document of sale between Charles Pole (seller) and Augustin Gwyn (purchaser). Gwyn, still owing money for the original purchase, sold shares in the ownership of the plantation in order to pay off his debt to Pole. Investors, named as the third party, who paid varying sums directly to Pole, include Simon Fanshawe of Hanover Square, Lewis Vickers of Holyhead, Patty Parsons of Hanover Square, Dorothy Askew of Wakefield, and numerous others. The document then records the sale of the estate by Gwyn to the fourth party, named as General Henry Clinton of Weybridge, and Matthew Brickdale of Clifton. The fifth and sixth named parties are listed as Charles Fanshawe of Inner Temple, William Bond of Walbrook, and Thomas and Clayton Case, who were Liverpool merchants and owners of slave ships. Charles Pole, 1695-1779, fifth son of Samuel Pole of Redbourne Hall, was a Liverpool merchant and Member of Parliament. Matthew Brickdale, 1735-1831, was a Bristol clothier, undertaker, and Member of Parliament who reportedly inherited £100,000 after the death of his father; he also owned the Hope Estate in St. Vincent and another plantation on Nevis. In 1832, prior to the abolition of slavery by the British in 1833, 61 enslaved women and 47 enslaved men were held in bondage on the Middleton Plantation.
  AM 2018-54
  Purchased in December 2017.
- Copy of Statistics on Enslaved Population from 1790 United States Census, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Consists of a 15-page manuscript copy (possibly made in 1830) of the first American census conducted in 1790, with statistics about the number of enslaved persons in each state, broken down by county. The only columns filled in are those labeled "slave population," "all other," and "total."
  AM 22077
  Gift of the Honorable George Henderson, Princeton Class of 1909, on June 21, 1950.
- Document Relating to the British Capture of Martinique, 1794-1795; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Consists of a ten-page manuscript copy of a document by British General Charles Grey and Vice Admiral John Jervis, extracted from the Registers of the Supreme Council of Martinique and translated into English from French. The document regards the British capture of Martinique from the French in 1794, complaints against prior French colonial rule of the island, and the status of enslaved persons, free people of color, and French settlers living on Martinique, among other subjects. It includes a threat to free people of color that British troops would treat them as enslaved if they were found armed. The document is docketed "Claim of Mon. Michel de Mallespine," and the first two pages include an affidavit by Marie Joseph Roignan, the wife of the Principal Register of the Sovereign Council of Martinique, Pierre Simon Roignan.
  AM 11409
  Gift of Charles August David Burk, Princeton Class of 1909, on April 26, 1937.
- Indenture of Elizabeth Winchester by Daniel Squire as Apprentice to Ebenezer and Sibyl Green, Belchertown, Massachusetts, 1796 September; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Manuscript indenture for a fourteen-year-old girl written by her guardian, apprenticing her to another family to learn the "Misteries of Housework" until her eighteenth birthday.
- Pierre-Marie Le Bozec Account Book of the French Cosair Républicaine, 1798-1799; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Consists of an eleven-page manuscript account book, titled "Livre C," documenting the financial accounts of the French cosair Républicaine under the command of French naval officer Pierre-Marie Le Bozec (1769-1830) in 1798 and 1799. In 1798, during the Quasi-War with the United States, the Républicaine captured the American vessel Alert, captained by Robert Gray. Le Bozec also used the Républicaine to seize and transport enslaved Africans. The Républicaine's privateering career ended in July 1799 when the vessel was captured off the coast of Surinam by the British frigate HMS Tamar with seventy captive Africans on board. The account book contains over 150 entries, including itemized lists of prizes taken during the vessel's high-seas privateering ventures just before the Napoleonic Wars.
  There are a number of entries documenting the ship's involvement with the slave trade, which record the purchase of clothing, shoes, food, and medicine intended for the enslaved Africans aboard the ship.
  AM 2012-67
  Purchased in February 2012.
- General Pierre Quantin (1759-1824) Letter to General Jean-Louis Ferrand (1758-1808) Concerning the Saint-Domingue Expedition, 1802 May 26-27; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Two-page letter from General Quantin at Fort Dauphin (Fort-Liberté), Haiti, to General Ferrand at Port-Margot, concerning French efforts to suppress the Haitian Revolution, specifically the Saint-Domingue expedition that was sent by Napoleon Bonaparte to restore French rule and slavery in the colony, which was in a state of insurgence by Toussaint Louverture's independence movement. The letter mentions the French Law of 20 May 1802 to reinstate slavery; the interception of supplies; Quantin's efforts to maintain control of Fort-Dauphin, which had recently been re-captured by French troops; the abandonment of two other forts by his colleagues; indigenous people who were deserting the island as refugees; and espionage and other efforts undertaken by his troops against the revolutionaries.
  Custodial History
  Marked with the stamp and catalogue number of the Bibliotheca Lindesiana, a private library owned by the Lindsays of Balcarres, Scotland.
  AM 2019-26
  Purchased in October 2018.
- Agreement and Invoice Regarding the Sale of Enslaved Persons and Cargo on Captain Miller F. Wickham's Ship Favourite, 1804 April 25; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Consists of a manuscript invoice and agreement between Captain Miller F. Wickham of Rhode Island (United States) and Philip Lewis and John Boyd of Cape Coast Castle (Ghana) for the sale of the entire cargo of Captain Wickham's ship Favourite, including eighty enslaved men and women described as "fair and merchantable slaves" and $7135.48 worth of supplies, including tobacco, alcohol, molasses, and other provisions. The invoice contains a detailed list of supplies and corresponding values.
  AM 12182
  Transferred from the General Manuscripts Miscellaneous Collection (C0140) in December 2008.
- Indentures for Domestic Apprenticeship of Two Children to Killian K. Van Rensselaer (1763-1845), Schenectady County, New York, 1808 April 21-1810 June 6; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Two printed and manuscript indentures for two children apprenticed as domestic servants to Killian K. Van Rensselaer (1763-1845), a United States Representative for New York. The 1808 indenture is for a four-year-old girl named Betty Ten Eyck, who is described as a "little black girl," from Lyden Ten Eyck. The 1810 indenture is for an eleven-year-old boy named Barent Dance from Walter Dance.
  AM 85-61
  Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Alan White Carrick, Princeton Class of 1923, on January 7, 1985.
- Bill of Sale of Enslaved Children Jupiter and Polly from Joseph Jackson to Robert Ogden, New Jersey, 1810; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Bill of sale for two enslaved children from Joseph Jackson in Rockaway, Morris County, New Jersey, to Robert Ogden in Sparta, Sussex County, New Jersey, for one dollar. The document names the children as Jupiter (born May 12, 1807) and Polly (born May 9, 1809) and indicates that their mother was named Abigail. The bill of sale, which refers to the gradual abolition of slavery in New Jersey, specifies that the children would remain enslaved until they reached the ages of 25 (for Jupiter) and 21 (for Polly).
  AM 2019-20
  Purchased in September 2018.
- Bill of Sale of Enslaved Woman Hannah from Jacob Cozine to Elizabeth Sprouls, New York, 1819 March 24; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 7)
  AM 16023
  Manuscript bill of sale of an enslaved "negro" woman for sixty dollars from Jacob Cozine of Flatbush, Kings County, New York, to Elizabeth Sprouls of Jamaica, Queens County, New York.
- Deed of Freedom for Manoel Creole from Catharine de Sena Gomes, Brazil, 1820 December 13; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Consists of a manuscript "carta de liberdade" written by Catharine de Sena Gomes of Brazil, freeing a formerly enslaved man named Manoel Creole for the price of 96 mil-réis.
  AM 14590
  Gift of Raleigh Hansl in 1952.
- Bill of Sale of Enslaved Girl Peggy from Henry R. Bledsoe, Tennessee, to Peter Loxente, Feliciana Parish, Louisiana, 1821 April 30; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 9)
  AM 12674
  Manuscript bill of sale of an enslaved eleven-year-old girl for 350 dollars.
- Valuation of Enslaved Laborers Owned by Berrald Innes, 1821 November 27-December 1; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Manuscript valuation of enslaved laborers, including one man (Martin), two women (Delphia and Poll), four children (Guy, Panelle, Anou, and Delphia), and an infant, formerly owned by the deceased Berrald Innes. The valuation was called for by Colonel Robert Innes and his brothers, among whom their brother's property would be split. The document is signed by Robert Innes, Hugh Innes, James Innes, Elizabeth E. Innes, and Harry James. The Innes family was likely from Fayette County, Kentucky.
- Indenture of Ann Ferril as Apprentice to William S. Barr by the Trustees of the Poor of New Castle County, Delaware, 1824 June 23; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Printed and manuscript indenture by trustees Joseph Grubb and Robert Forwood for a four-year-old girl described as a "poor coloured Child," apprenticing her until her eighteenth birthday to learn "housewifery," reading, writing, and arithmetic.
- John Lavicount Estate and Antigua Legal Documents, 1829 September-1841; 2 boxes
  Consists of Antiguan financial and legal documents from the decade in which slavery was abolished on the island (1834). There are receipts and accounts documenting barrels of corn meal purchased at specified prices to maintain African and/or African-Antiguan people enslaved by John Lavicount Sr. on his plantation on Antigua.
  AM 2008-116
  Purchased in June 2008.
  - Accounts of John Lavicount Sr. for Corn Meal Purchased to Maintain Enslaved Laborers on his Antigua Plantation, 1829 September-1830 January; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Consists of a manuscript booklet and account sheet recording Lavicount's purchases of corn meal from Richard B. Eldridge under the Amelioration Act of 1798.
  - Case of Antony Musgrave, Treasurer, vs. William Simpson, Acting Collector, Antigua, 1830; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Document of the Court of Common Pleas for Antigua regarding a financial dispute.
  - Recapitulation of Accounts of Augusta Maria Lavicount and the John Lavicount Estate with Ewart Myers and Company, Antigua, 1841 December 31; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Document of the Court of Chancery for Antigua.
- "List of Slaves and Stock on Three Mile River Estate", 1830 January 1; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Consists of a nine-page manuscript list of enslaved men, women, and children, as well as livestock, on the Westmoreland, Jamaica, plantation of James Graham Crawfuird of Gartur, Scotland.
  AM 2008-99
  Purchased in April 2008.
- Deed of Sale of Enslaved Men Sam and James from Mark Davis to John Budd Slawson, New Orleans, Louisiana, 1842 June 11; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Manuscript and printed deed of sale for two enslaved men, Sam (age 23) and James (alias "Charles," age 21), for 1150 dollars.
  AM 10795
  Gift of George M. Peck in 1934.
- Bill of Sale of Enslaved Boy Neptune from James E. Hogg to Mary E. Howard, Grahamville, South Carolina, 1845 December 19; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Printed and manuscript bill of sale of an enslaved boy for 372 dollars.
- Inventory of the Estate of Edward Engelhard, Hinds County, Mississippi, 1848; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 20)
  Consists of an inventory and appraisal of the "goods, chattels, and personal estate" of the deceased Edward Engelhard, which lists household items and supplies, as well as enslaved persons, including Fanny (24 years old) along with her three children, Jane, Alverten, and Washington, Moses (43 years old), Billy (17 years old), Alfred (17 years old), Tolbert (12 years old), and Mary (14 years old).
  AM 2019-21
- Elisha Embree (1801-1863) Letter to William Anderson Porter (1800–1884) Regarding the Expansion of Slavery into California and New Mexico, 1848 July 21; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Two-page letter, marked "confidential," from Embree, who was then United States Representative for Indiana, to Porter, who was an Indiana politician and judge, soliciting Porter's help with raising funds to support canvassing in his district related to congressional debates over the extension of slavery into the newly acquired California and New Mexico territories.
  AM 2019-27
- Deed and Receipt of Sale of Enslaved Man Frederick from Miss M. E. Bowen to H. Meinhard and his Brother, Savannah, Georgia, 1859 May 16; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 16)
  AM 1382
  Manuscript and printed title and receipt for the sale of an enslaved man around 20 years old for 1130 dollars, along with a manuscript confirmation of payment received.
- Bill of Sale of Enslaved Man Sam, Louisville, Kentucky, 1861; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Manuscript bill of sale for an enslaved eighteen-year-old man for 700 dollars from W. Fishback [?] to T.M. [?] Swann.
- Complaint of Dukelet Askew on Behalf of William H. Anderson (Deceased) Against George W. Ashford, Hinds County, Mississippi, 1860 January-1861 April; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Consists of a document recording a complaint of Dukelet ("Duke") Askew, administrator of the estate of William H. Anderson, deceased, against George W. Ashford in the Confederate Circuit Court of Hinds County, Mississippi. Askew's complaint accuses Ashford of breaching his agreement to pay $582 for the loan of two of laborers named Cary and John who were enslaved by Anderson. Inside the document, which is dated April 1861, there are two promissory notes dated January 1860 and labeled as "Exhibit A" and "Exhibit B."
- Promissory Note to Nath Tyler for the Hire of an Enslaved Man John from William Phillips, 1863 November 30; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Printed and manuscript promissory note for the hire of a "negro slave" from the period from January 1, 1864, to January 1, 1865, for five hundred dollars ("Confederate currency").
- Documents on Slavery in Brazil, 1758-1888; Susan Bach (Firm)‏; 1 box
  Consists of 77 miscellaneous legal and other documents, as well as one book, dating from 1758 to 1888, pertaining to the history of the history of slavery in Brazil as a Portuguese colony and later as the Empire of Brazil, until the abolition of slavery in 1887. These documents provide insight into the slave trade, plantation economy, and lives of enslaved Afro-Brazilians and their families.
  Arrangement
  Materials are arranged as received by the repository.
  AM 2018-105